Okay, so let's start class.
好的，开始上课吧。
I'm going to review very quickly what we did last class.
我会快速回顾上节课的内容。
So last class we learned about monotheism,
上节课我们学习了单神论。
which
哪一个
is the idea of one true God.
是一个真神的概念。
And as I said last class,
正如我上节课所说，
this marked an intellectual revolution in human history.
这标志着人类历史上的一次知识革命。
And for monotheism, we developed three new ideas,
而在单神论中，我们发展了三种新思想，
which are money,
它们是货币、
individual,
个体，
and the nation state.
和民族国家。
It's important to note that
重要的是要注意到
these ideas have always existed in human history,
这些思想在人类历史中一直存在，
but with monotheism, these ideas became the dominant paradigm.
但在单神论出现后，这些思想成为主导范式。
And together,
并且它们一起，
they will give us modernity
它们将为我们带来现代性
and create the world that
并创造我们今天所处的世界
we live in today.
我们正生活其中
So that's what we discussed last class.
所以这就是我们上节课讨论的内容。
And remember last class, we also discussed that
记得上节课，我们还讨论了这一点。
this created a lot of problems for us.
这给我们带来了很多问题。
There are a lot of benefits, but there are also a lot of consequences.
有许多好处，也有许多后果。
So we're going to continue the story of humanity today.
于是我们继续讲述当今人类的故事。
And today, I want to focus on a very specific question.
今天，我要聚焦一个非常具体的问题。
Why do societies rise and why do they fall?
为什么社会会兴起，又会衰落？
And I know that
我知道
these first few classes may seem abstract
这前几节课看起来可能抽象
and theoretical, but that's because
并且理论化，但那是因为
we're developing the ethical models in order to better understand our world.
我们正在制定伦理模型，以更好地理解我们的世界
So as we move on, we'll start looking at very concrete examples.
于是我们继续前进，开始研究非常具体的例子
But for the first few classes, please be patient.
但在前几节课里，请耐心等待。
We are going to develop a theory to understand the world.
我们将构建理论来理解世界。
So let's discuss societies,
于是我们来讨论社会。
why they rise and
为什么它们崛起
why they decline.
为什么它们衰落
Now, unfortunately, we live in a world in decline.
现在不幸的是，我们正处于一个衰落的世界
So there are lots of signs that
于是有许多迹象
the world is in decline.
世界正处于衰落之中
What are these signs?
这些迹象是什么？
Shout out some signs.
列举一些迹象。
Yeah, very good.
好的，很好。
So you have conflict and wars.
于是你就有冲突和战争。
You look at the situation in Ukraine.
你看看乌克兰的局势。
Look at the situation in the Middle East.
再看看中东的局势。
But also, you may have seen the news
另外，你可能已经看到新闻。
and you have seen conflicts arising in Southeast Asia, Thailand,
以及你已经看到东南亚的冲突在泰国、缅甸出现。
Myanmar. Also, Trump is about to sell his country.
另外，特朗普正准备把他的国家卖掉。
He's about to send U.S. troops to Mexico and Venezuela.
他正准备把美军派往墨西哥和委内瑞拉。
So we live in a world of conflict.
于是我们生活在冲突的世界里。
And that tells us that the world is in decline.
这说明世界正处于衰落之中。
What are some other signs?
还有哪些其他迹象？
Environment. Good, yes.
环境。好的，没错。
So you have climate change.
所以你有气候变化。
We are putting too much pressure on the environment.
我们对环境施加过大压力。
So the air, the water,
于是空气、河水、土地都变得更有毒。
the land is becoming much more toxic.
好的。还有什么？
Good. What else? Good, yes.
好的，没错。
Unemployment is going up.
失业率在上升。
But not only that, but people's attitude towards work is declining.
但不止于此，大家对工作的态度也在下降。
We live in an age when
我们正处于一个时代…
people don't take work that seriously.
人们不再把工作当回事。
People are not as enthusiastic.
人们的热情不再那么高。
They're not as motivated to work hard as before.
他们不像以前那样有劲儿去努力工作。
We call this in China the Bailan age, right?
我们把这叫做中国的摆烂时代，对吧？
The age of Bailan, meaning let it rot.
摆烂时代，意为让它腐烂。
Like, who cares? Don't take things too seriously.
比如，谁在乎？别把事儿想得太认真。
In America, the term is called quite quitting.
在美国，这个词叫做“相当放弃”。
You pretend to work, but you're not really working.
你表面上在工作，却并没有真正工作。
What are some other signs?
还有哪些其他迹象？
So also, you have lower birth rate.
于是，你的出生率也下降了。
And this is a very important sign, right?
这也是一个非常重要的标志，对吧？
Because if you think about it,
因为如果你想想看，
if young people refuse to get married
如果年轻人不结婚并且有孩子，最终世界就会消亡，对吧？
and have babies, eventually the world is going to die off, right?
于是这实际上是一个非常重要的标志，说明世界正在衰落。
So this is actually a very important sign that the world is in decline.
And we're seeing this happen throughout the entire world in all societies.
我们在全世界各个社会中都看到这种情况发生。
The only exception is Israel and Georgia.
唯一例外是以色列和格鲁吉亚。
But these are very small, rare cases.
但这些只是很小很少的例子。
For most societies,
对大多数社会而言，
there's rapid decline in birth rate.
出生率迅速下降。
What are some other signs?
还有哪些其他迹象？
You see a lower
你会看到生活水平下降。
standard of living.
并且这意味着通胀。
And all this means is that inflation, right?
And all this means isthat inflation, right?
So people make less money, and they can afford less.
于是人们收入减少，消费也随之减少。
Prices go up, but people's wages go down.
物价上涨，工资却下降。
So that's another sign of decline.
这又是衰落的又一标志。
What are some other signs?
还有哪些其他迹象？
Now it's like diabetes or high blood pressure.
现在就像糖尿病或高血压。
Okay. You also see higher stress, right?
好的，你也会看到更高的压力，对吗？
Higher stress, people feel more anxious.
更高的压力，人们更焦虑。
People feel more depressed. People feel more stressed.
人们更抑郁，压力更大。
Emotionally, they feel drained.
情感上，他们感到精疲力竭。
Okay, what else? Okay,
好的，另外还有什么？
people are less optimistic, right?
人们的乐观度下降了，对吗？
Okay. Greater pessimism.
好的，悲观情绪更浓。
Okay. Also, this is really important, is the idea of debt.
好的，另外，这个债务的概念真的很重要。
Right? Both public and private.
对吗？既有公共债务也有私人债务。
There are lots of governments around the world that are facing a fiscal crisis.
世界各地有许多政府正面临财政危机。
A fiscal crisis just means that
财政危机只是意味着
they spend more than they take in in tax revenue.
他们的支出超过税收收入。
There are many families in China,
中国有许多家庭。
in the United States, throughout the world that are heavily in debt. Okay, so
在美国，世界各地都深陷债务。好了，
debt is a huge issue for the world today.
债务是当今世界的重大问题。
Also, lower cohesion
此外，凝聚力下降。
and trust.
和信任。
And what this means is that
而这意味着
people no longer trust each
人们不再信任
other as they did before.
其他如他们以前所做的那样。
Society is less cohesive.
社会凝聚力下降。
If you see, if you walk on the street and
如果你看到，如果你走在街上…
you see a man on the street bleeding or hurt,
你看到街上有人流血或受伤，
you're less likely to help him.
你就不太可能去帮他。
Okay, and this is very true not only in China
好的，这点在中国也很真实。
but also elsewhere as well.
也在其他地方一样。
So lower trust issues.
于是信任度下降。
What are some other signs?
还有哪些其他迹象？
Disease. Okay, greater disease, yeah.
疾病。好的，疾病增多了。
Okay, increase in disease.
好的，疾病增多。
People are less healthy than before.
人们的健康状况比以前差。
People are more stressed than before.
人们比以前更紧张。
People are less optimistic.
人们更不乐观。
So we can go on and on and on.
于是我们可以继续继续继续。
Because the signs of rapid social decline are too many.
因为快速社会衰退的迹象太多了。
Now, these are signs of decline.
现在，这些就是衰退的迹象。
Well, if we look at rise, then obviously it's the opposite, right?
好吧，如果我们看上升，显然就是相反的，对吧？
People are much more willing to trust each other.
人们更愿意互相信任。
Rather than going into debt, people will save money.
人们不再借债，而是存钱。
People are healthier. People are much more optimistic.
人们更健康，更乐观。
People are
人们在
having lots
有很多
and lots of babies, right?
并且有很多宝宝，对吧？
Okay. People are employed.
好的。人们有工作。
Okay? So these are all signs
好的？所以这些都是迹象
that society is in decline.
表明社会正在衰落。
The rise, it's the opposite.
上升，正好相反。
Also, another sign of decline that's very important
另外，还有一个非常重要的衰落迹象
that doesn't really happen in China, what happens in the Western world is immigration.
在中国并不常见，西方出现的是移民。
Okay? Immigration.
好的？移民。
Immigration is a huge issue in the Western world,
移民是西方的一个大问题，
and we will discuss immigration in future classes.
我们将在后续课程中讨论移民。
But immigration is a sign of decline because
但移民是衰落的迹象，因为它减少了凝聚力。
it reduces cohesion.
好？它还降低了生活水平。
Okay? And it also reduces the standard of living. Okay?
好？
Another sign of decline is also housing prices.
另一个衰落的迹象是房价。
So, people can no longer afford to buy a house.
于是人们再也买不起房子。
This is true in China.
这在中国也是真的。
Young people can no longer afford to buy a house.
年轻人再也买不起房子。
But it's also true throughout the world.
但这在全球也同样。
Okay? It's really hard for young people to get by.
年轻人真的很难过活。
Okay? All right.
好的？好了。
Also, fiscal crisis.
还有，财政危机。
Right? We talked about this. But
对吧？我们说过这个。但
the idea of fiscal crisis is the government cannot afford a lot of public,
财政危机的概念是政府无法承担大量公共支出。
public expenditures.
未来，或许多五、十年后，…。
In the future, maybe five, ten years from now,
…
pension will be a huge problem for governments.
养老金将成为政府的巨大问题。
Okay? So, these are all signs of rapid decline.
好吧？所以，这些都是快速衰退的迹象。
All right. Now, having done this,
好了。现在，完成了这一切。
what I'm going to do now is go
我现在要做的事是去梳理一些理论，解释为什么会出现这种情况。
over some theories as to why this is happening.
世界为何衰退？】
Why is the world in decline?
Why is the worldin decline?
Okay? And there are lots and lots of theories.
好的？还有很多很多理论。
But I will present three theories to you
但我会给你介绍三个我觉得有趣的理论。
that I think are interesting.
that I think areinteresting.
Okay? The first is the idea of financialization. And
好的？第一条是金融化的概念。且
this theory is proposed
这个理论是由一位经济学家提出的。
by an economist,
a French economist named Thomas Piketty.
一位名叫托马斯·皮凯蒂的法国经济学家。
Piketty. Okay? And he wrote a book called Capital.
皮凯蒂。好的吗？他写了一本叫《资本》 的书。
Capital in the 21st Century.
《21 世纪的资本》。
It is a fantastic book.
这本书很精彩。
You don't have to read the book, but if you have a chance, you should definitely pick it up.
不必一定读，但若有机会，最好去拿起读一读。
Because it is a very easy but
因为它非常容易但
very illuminating read.
非常有启发性的阅读。
And what he argues is
而他所论证的是
that what happens in society is
社会中发生的事是
that capitalism transitions from face to face to face.
资本主义从一个面向另一个面转移。
In the beginning, you have consumer.
一开始，你就有消费者。
Capitalism. Meaning that
资本主义。其含义是。
what the society is trying to do is create goods
社会所做的事是制造消费者想买的商品。
that consumers want to buy.
这是一段快速财富生成的时代。
This is an era of rapid wealth generation. Then
This is an era of rapidwealth generation. Then
you move into financial capitalism,
你进入金融资本主义，[184]
which is a period of investment.
这是一段投资时期。[185]
Rather than build factories,
不再建造工厂，而是……[186]
you put the money into the stock market.
你把钱投入股市。
Okay? So,
好的？那么，
you're trying to generate as much money as possible.
你正努力把钱做得尽可能多。
But what we discussed last class that's very important is wealth
但我们上节课讨论的非常重要的内容是财富
and money are not the same thing.
和钱不是同一回事。
So, in the first phase, consumer capitalism,
所以，在第一阶段，消费资本主义中。
you focus on the generation of wealth.
你专注于财富的生成。
In financial capitalism, you focus on the generation of money.
在金融资本主义中，你专注于钱的生成。
And then
然后呢。
you move on to monopoly capitalism,
你进入了垄断资本主义的阶段，
which is where
在这里，
just a few
仅仅是几家
companies control everything.
公司掌控一切。
And we live in an era of monopoly capitalism.
我们正处于垄断资本主义时代。
And this happens because
这之所以发生是因为
it is much more profitable
对公司来说，成为垄断比相互竞争更有利可图。
for companies to be monopolies than
to be in competition with each other.
对公司来说，成为垄断比相互竞争更有利可图。
Financial capitalism...
金融资本主义…
is looking to create as much money as possible, not as much wealth.
它正在寻求创造尽可能多的钱，而不是尽可能多的财富。
And so, a few companies come to dominate, become monopolies.
于是，少数公司崛起，成为垄断。
And that's the age we live in today.
而这就是我们今天所处的时代。
Now, why is this important?
现在，为什么这很重要？
It's important because...
重要的原因是……
when we make this transition,
当我们完成这一步转变时，
people are no longer focused on working hard.
人们不再专注于勤劳工作。
They're only focused on speculating.
他们只专注于投机。
Alright? So, let me give you an example.
好的？那我给你举个例子。
Let's just say I'm an entrepreneur.
假设我是个创业者。
And I want to make as much money as possible.
我想尽可能赚大钱。
Well, what I do is I build a factory.
好吧，我的做法是建个工厂。
When I build a factory, I'm creating real wealth.
当我建工厂时，我在创造真正的财富。
Because a factory requires you to hire workers.
因为工厂需要雇佣工人。
It requires you to build technology.
它需要你去研发技术。
It requires you to build goods that people want to buy.
它需要你制造人们想买的商品。
But after I build a factory and I make a lot of money,
但当我建好工厂并赚到很多钱后，
I want to take this money and let it grow as fast as possible.
我想把这笔钱投入，让它尽快增长。
So, I put it in a stock market.
于是，我把它投进股市。
Okay? And that's just how people behave.
好吧？这就是人们的常规操作。
The problem is that if too many people do
问题是如果太多人都这么做，结果就没人真正工作。
that, then no one's really working.
没人真正创造经济中的真实财富。
No one's creating real wealth in the economy.
No one's creating realwealth in the economy.
The other problem is that...
另一个问题是……
because of the way capitalism is set up,
因为资本主义的设定方式，
if everyone's putting the money in a stock market, the stock market grows too fast.
如果大家都把钱投进股市，股市就会增长得太快。
And the real economy does not grow that fast.
而实体经济并不会这么快增长。
Okay? And the difference is stark.
好的？差距很明显。
Thomas Piketty spent a lot of time going over income tax.
托马斯·皮凯蒂花了很多时间研究所得税。
Just looking at how much tax people paid.
只看人们缴纳的税额。
He did a lot of statistical analysis.
他做了大量统计分析。
And what he discovered is the real economy in late -stage capitalism
他发现的是真正经济在后期资本主义中的表现。
will grow about 2%.
将增长约2%。
The financial economy will grow at 5%.
金融经济将增长5%。
Okay? And this is really key.
好的吗？这点很关键。
What this is telling us is that if you have a million dollars,
这句话告诉我们，如果你有一百万美元，
you could choose to go and open a restaurant,
你可以选择去开一家餐馆，
or you could choose to invest in the stock market.
或者你可以选择去投资股市。
If you open a restaurant,
如果你开一家餐馆，
you will make at most $20,000 a year.
你一年最多能赚两万美元。
But if you were to put it in the stock market, you would make $50,000 a year.
如果你把钱投进股市，一年能赚五万美元。
So everyone's going to put all the money in the stock market,
于是大家都把钱投入股市，于是股市就能上涨。
which allows for the stock market to increase.
但实体经济并没有改善。
But the real economy is not improving.
And therefore, you have all these issues arise.
于是就出现了这些问题。
Greater unemployment, greater debt.
失业率上升，债务增加。
No one's really working.
没人真正在工作。
Okay? So that's the idea of financialization.
好的？这就是金融化的概念。
And what Piketty argues is that
而皮凯蒂所说的是，
this is just a natural cycle.
这只是一个自然循环。
This is just a natural byproduct of capitalism.
这只是资本主义的自然副产。
We live in a stage, we live in an age of late -stage capitalism.
我们处在一个阶段，处在晚期资本主义的时代。
Is this clear to you guys?
你们听懂了吗？
Any questions before I move on
还有问题吗？
to the second theory?
接下来是第二个理论吗？
All right. Let's move on to the second theory called elite overproduction.
好的，接下来是第二个理论——精英过剩。
And this was proposed by a
这由一位名叫彼得·图尔奇恩的历史学家提出。
historian named Peter Turchin. And
彼得·图尔奇恩花了几十年时间研究社会兴起的原因。
Peter Turchin spent decades looking at why societies rise
Peter Turchin spent decadeslooking at why societies rise
and fall. He looked at the Roman Empire.
他研究了罗马帝国的兴衰。
He looked at the French Revolution.
他研究了法国大革命。
He looked at many different examples.
他研究了许多不同的例子。
And what he believed is
而他所相信的是
societies fall,
社会会衰落、衰退、崩溃，因精英过剩的想法。
decline, collapse, because of the idea of elite overproduction.
Meaning you have too many
意思是你有太多
powerful people competing for limited positions of power.
强势人物争夺有限的权力位置。
All right? So to understand this,
好了？所以要理解这个，
I'm going to talk about another experiment called rat utopia.
我将谈谈另一个实验，叫做“老鼠乌托邦”。
And
而且
rat utopia was a series of experiments
“老鼠乌托邦”是一系列实验。
conducted by an American scientist named James B.
由美国科学家詹姆斯·B·卡尔霍恩主持的实验。
Calhoun. And he said,
他还说，
what's the difference between And what James Calhoun was trying to do in his
什么是……与詹姆斯·卡尔霍恩在他的实验中尝试做的事之间的区别
experiments was trying to figure out what living in a world of abundance
实验是想弄清在丰盛、富足与安定的世界里生活意味着什么。
and wealth and security meant.
在第二次世界大战之后，…
After World War II,
After World WarII,
the world was divided between the United States and the Soviet Union.
世界被美国和苏联分割。
It was the Cold War. But
那是冷战。但……
it was also a time of increasing abundance due to technology
那也是技术带来丰盛的时代。
and peace.
和和平。
And the population was increasing.
人口在增长。
So James Calhoun conducted these experiments to figure out what this meant for the world.
于是詹姆斯·卡尔霍恩开展这些实验，以弄清这对世界意味着什么。
So what he did was this.
于是他做了这件事。
He had a room, okay, that was sealed off from the world.
他准备了一个房间，好的，那个房间与外界隔离。
And in the room, he put in food
在房间里，他放了食物。
and water and housing for a colony of rats.
和水以及为一群老鼠提供住所。
Maybe like 10 rats at first.
一开始大约十只老鼠。
But they quickly, um,
但它们很快，嗯，
became 400, 500 rats.
变成400、500只老鼠。
And at first, the rats were really happy.
起初，老鼠们非常开心。
But no matter how Calhoun,
但无论Calhoun怎样，
um, configured the experiment,
嗯，配置实验，
ultimately, the rats always ended up killing each other.
最终，老鼠总是互相杀死。
Okay? So what he discovered is
好的？所以他发现的就是。
if you live in a world of abundance and security,
如果你生活在丰裕与安全的世界里，
the end result is, the rats always kill each other.
最终结果是，老鼠总是互相杀死。
And he kept on doing this for 20 years.
他又继续做了二十年。
And he could never, ever
他总是……
create a situation in which the rats lived peacefully.
创造一个老鼠能安然相处的局面。
And he could never figure out why this was the case.
他也没能弄清楚原因。
And even today, there's a huge debate as to why this is the case.
而且至今，关于此事的辩论仍然巨大。
But he had a theory, okay?
但他有一个理论，行吗？
And the theory is this.
这个理论是这样的。
The rats were not competing for food.
老鼠们并不是在争食物。
They were really competing for status.
它们真正争的是地位。
All right. So,
好的，明白了。
let's think about this, okay? In a state of nature,
先来想想这个，行吗？在自然状态下，
in the real world, rats compete each other for mating rights,
在现实世界里，老鼠互相竞争交配权利，
right? So, uh, you see a beautiful rat,
对吧？所以，你看到一只漂亮的老鼠，
and you, you fight over her, right?
你们也会为她争斗，对吧？
The rat who wins out is now the alpha male.
赢得胜利的老鼠现在就是α雄。
And the alpha male can have as many female companions as he wants.
α雄可以随心所欲地拥有任意多的雌伴。
Okay? And what do the other rats do?
好的？其他老鼠会怎么做？
In nature, what will the other rats do?
在自然状态下，其他老鼠会怎样？
Well, the other rats will probably run away, go somewhere else,
嗯，其他老鼠大概会跑开，去别处去。
and find other female companions, right?
并且去找其他雌伴，对吧？
Because everyone's trying to be the alpha male.
因为大家都想成为α雄。
But in, what's the problem with James Calhoun's experiment?
但在这里，贾姆斯·卡尔霍恩实验有什么问题？
Why do they fight each other?
它们为什么互相争斗？
There's no place for them to go.
它们没有去处可去。
They're stuck where they are.
它们被困在原地。
You understand? So,
你明白了吗？所以，
status is what we call a zero -sum game.
状态就是我们所说的零和游戏。
I win, you lose.
我赢，你输。
Okay? There can only be one winner.
好的？只能有一个赢家。
But, in nature,
但是，在自然界，
if I win, then the other rats run away
如果我赢了，其他老鼠就会跑掉。
and try to figure out, try to, try to build their own colony.
并尝试去弄清楚，尝试，尝试去建造自己的殖民。
But in James Calhoun's experiment, there's no place for them to go.
但在詹姆斯·卡尔霍恩的实验里，他们没有去处。
And so, all that happens is they keep on fighting each other until
于是，所有的事就是他们一直互相争斗。
they, they die. Okay?
他们，他们死了。好吗？
And that's the idea of elite overproduction.
这就是精英过度繁衍的概念。
And that's what Peter Turchin says.
这正是彼得·图尔奇所说的。
The elite, the children of the elite, are always in the middle.
精英，精英的子嗣，始终在中间。
Fighting for positions of power.
争夺权力位置。
Not normal people, it's the children of the elite.
非普通人，乃精英之子嗣。
But eventually, they have too many children
但最终，他们的子嗣太多了
and there are not enough positions of power.
而且权力位置不够用
Okay? Another, another way of saying this is that
好吧？换个说法就是
in China today, there are too many graduates of Peking University,
在今天的中国，清华大学的毕业生太多了
Beida, and Tsinghua University.
清华，没错？他们想当大老板。
Tsinghua, right? They want to be the big boss.
They want to have the power.
他们想掌握权力。
But there's too many of them. Okay?
但他们太多了，好吧？
There's no, and there's no place for them to go.
又没有，且他们也没有去处。
And that leads to conflict in society.
这导致社会冲突。
And ultimately, what Peter Turchin has discovered is,
最终，彼得·图尔奇发现的是，
if that's the case, then
如果是这样的话，
elite overproduction will ultimately lead to either war or revolution.
精英过剩最终会导致战争或革命。
It will lead to the collapse of society.
它将导致社会崩溃。
And there's no way around this.
没有办法绕过此。
Okay? That's Peter Turchin.
好的？那就是彼得·图尔奇。
Now, I want to go to the third theory.
现在，我想进入第三个理论。
And the third theory is the idea of a
第三个理论是……
civilizational life cycle.
文化生命周期。
And this is proposed by a German philosopher,
并且这由一位德国哲学家提出，
scholar named Oswald Spangler.
名为奥斯瓦尔德·斯潘格尔。
And what he argues is that
而他所论证的是
society, culture, civilization, it's no different from a person.
社会、文化、文明，跟个人没有区别。
As a person, as a human being, we go through a life cycle.
作为个人，作为人类，我们经历人生周期。
We are born, we grow up, we mature,
我们出生，成长，成熟，然后死亡。对吗？
then we die. Right?
而且没有办法绕过这一步。
And there's no way around this.
We all have limited life cycles.
我们都有有限的生命周期。
You can live to 100.
你可以活到一百岁。
You can live to 150. But eventually you'll die.
你可以活到一百五十岁。但最终你会死去。
And what Oswald Spangler said, is that
而奥斯瓦尔德·斯潘格尔所说的，正是如此
happens in society as well.
这同样在社会中发生着
And there's nothing anyone can do about this.
而且无论谁都无能为此做什么
So let's go over the life cycle for civilization.
那么我们来梳理一下文明的生命周期。
Okay? In the beginning, you are in the village.
好的？一开始，你在村庄里。
Then you move to the town.
然后你搬到城镇。
Then you move to the city.
Then you develop the mega city.
然后你发展成大都市。
Okay? Not all civilizations will go through this cycle.
好？并非所有文明都经历这个循环。
But the successful ones, will go through this cycle.
但成功的会经历这个循环。
Okay? You start off, so the Romans, right?
好？你先从罗马开始，对吧？
The Qing Dynasty. You start off in a village.
好？先从村庄开始。
Then, if you're successful in the village, you build a town.
然后，如果你在村庄成功，你就建城镇。
Then, when you're in a town,
然后，当你在城镇时，
and you're successful, you defeat other towns, and you build a city, and you become a mega city.
然后，你成功后，征服其他城镇，建成城市，成为大都市。
Okay? And what Oswald Spangler says is, at the height of the civilization,
好的？奥斯瓦尔德·斯潘格尔说，文明巅峰时，文明就该消亡。
the civilization must now die.
好的？于是，】
Okay? So,
好的？
let's go over the theory.
让我们来回顾一下理论。
Well, in the village, life is pretty simple.
在村庄里，生活相当简单。
People work hard.
人们勤劳工作。
Okay? They are united.
好的？他们团结在一起。
They have a collective mentality.
他们拥有集体思维。
Everyone's helping each other. And also, what's really important is,
大家互相帮助。更重要的是……
lots of babies, right?
很多小宝宝，对吧？
It's very common for, you know,
很常见，嗯，
mothers to give birth to 10,
母亲们会生十个孩子
11 kids in a village.
村里有11个孩子。
Right? And the reason why is, kids are free labor.
对吧？之所以如此，是因为孩子们是自由劳动力。
So, you're incentivized to have as many children as possible.
于是你就会被激励尽可能多生孩子。
Okay. So, this is the framework of a village.
好的。这样就是村落的框架。
But, as you go up the civilization ladder,
但当你攀升文明阶梯时，
as you mature as a civilization,
随着文明的成熟，
what happens is,
发生的事是，
you have increased abstraction.
你有了更高层的抽象。
Abstraction is just a fancy word for, you're removed from reality.
抽象只是个花哨词，意思是你已脱离现实。
Okay? So, when you're in a village, you understand everything, right?
好的？那么，当你在村里时，你就能理解一切，对吧？
You understand, oh, the food that
你明白，哦，吃的食物是
I eat comes from the seeds I implant.
我种下的种子发出的。
Right? But when you're in a city, guess what?
对吧？但你在城里，猜猜是什么？
That those drinks you're drinking, you have no idea where it comes from.
你喝的那杯饮料，你根本不知道它来自哪儿。
Right? The food you're eating, you have no idea where it comes from.
你吃的那顿饭，你根本不知道它来自哪儿。
It's all abstract to you.
一切都抽象化了。
It's all removed from reality.
一切都脱离了现实。
Okay? Um, so,
好吧？呃，
in the village, people are engaged in working hard
在村里，人们勤劳工作
and in helping each other.
并互相帮助。
But as you move up, people become much more individualistic.
但随着层级上升，人们变得更具个人性。
Right? You're concerned about your own personal pleasure.
对吧？你在乎自己的个人乐趣。
You're concerned about what,
你在乎什么，
how do I derive benefit from this?
我怎样从中获得收益？
Okay? So, another way of saying this is, in a village,
好的？所以，另一种说法是，在一个村庄里
what keeps people together are emotions and tradition
情感与传统以及关系把人们聚在一起
and relationships.
情感、传统与关系
But when you move to a megacity, what is it that holds people together?
但当你搬到大都市时，是什么把人们聚在一起？
It's money. Right?
就是钱。对吧？
Money is the greatest abstraction.
钱是最大的抽象。
The problem with money is that
钱的问题在于
it means we don't have to ever change.
它意味着我们不必再改变。
We trust each other. In a village,
我们彼此信任。在村里，
if you get sick, everyone comes and helps you.
如果你生病，大家都会来帮你。
Right? But in the city, if you get sick,
对吧？但在城市里，如果你生病，
you go to the hospital and pay the doctor.
你去医院付医生费。
Your neighbors don't have to care.
你的邻居不必关心。
Your family doesn't have to help you.
家人不必帮你。
Okay? So you become individualized.
好的？于是你变得个体化。
You become atomized.
你变得原子化。
Okay? And in the megacity,
好吧？而在大都市，
what happens is, because
发生的事是，因为
you are concerned only about your own individual pleasure,
只关心自己的个人快乐
you don't work hard anymore.
你不再努力工作了。
In fact, what you want to do is,
实际上，你想做的是，
you want immigrants to work for you.
你想让移民为你工作。
Right? You no longer care about other people.
对吧？你不再关心别人了。
All you care about is yourself. And guess what, guys?
你只关心自己。你猜怎么了，伙计们？
You don't want to have any children.
你不想要孩子。
Okay? And
好吧？还有
that's why the megacity represents the death of civilization.
这就是为什么大都市代表文明的衰亡。
Okay? And what is Beijing?
好吧？那北京是什么？
What is Shanghai?
上海是什么？
What is Washington DC?
华盛顿特区是什么？
What is New York? What is Paris?
纽约是什么？巴黎又是什么？
What is London? They're all megacities.
伦敦是什么？它们都是大都市。
Okay? And
好吧？还有
that's why we have these trends.
这就是我们有这些趋势的原因。
And what Oswald Spengler says is,
而奥斯瓦尔德·斯彭格勒所说的是，
there's nothing anyone can do about this.
这件事谁也做不了什么。
It is a natural life cycle.
它是自然的生命周期。
All right? So these are the three major theories.
好的？所以这就是三大理论。
I want you guys to remember.
我想让你们记住。
Okay? Sorry.
好的？抱歉。
Can you give the microphone? Yeah.
你能递麦吗？好的。
Can you just speak in the front row? Audience member 1 But
你能在前排说吗？观众1
what if there is a universal target that
如果有一个统一目标，迫使大家一起合作呢？
forces everyone needs to work together?
你知道，这样会不会成功吗？
You know, will that work out to like,
everyone just put down all of these problems
大家把这些问题都放下来
and figure out that, like,
然后想想，像是这样
Yeah, okay, I understand.
好的，我懂了
That is a great question, okay?
那是个很好的问题，好的？
So the question, to rephrase it, okay, is,
所以问题，重新表述一下，好的，是，
yeah, but what if there's an external threat,
是的，但如果有外部威胁，
okay? An external threat.
好的？外部威胁。
If there's an external threat,
如果有外部威胁，
then
那么
surely this system,
当然这个系统，
this life cycle, can be extended, right?
这个生命周期，可以延伸，吧？
And external threats are examples of, hey, let's say there's an alien invasion.
而外部威胁是例子，嘿，假设有外星侵袭。
Let's just say China's being attacked by the United States,
假设中国被美国攻击，
right?
对吧？
And unfortunately, the answer is no.
不幸的是，答案是没有。
It does not matter. Because
这不重要。因为
once you've reached the point of a megacity,
一旦你们达到了大都市的阶段，
first of all, you're so selfish,
首先，你很自私，
you're self -absorbed, you are not aware of external threats.
你自我沉浸，未察外部威胁。
The other issue is you're no longer capable of working together
另一个问题是你们不再能一起工作
because you don't trust each other, okay?
因为你们互不信任，好吗？
So the external threats factor doesn't really matter.
外部威胁因素其实不重要。
But that's a great question. Thank you for asking, okay?
这确实是个好问题。谢谢你的提问，好吗？
Yes, in theory, oh my God, if aliens come, then humans would unite.
是的，理论上，哦我的天啊，如果外星人来了，人类就会团结。
No, that's not what would happen, okay?
不，那不是会发生的事，好的？
What would happen is certain factions of humans would try to align the aliens to conquer everyone else.
什么会发生的是，某些人类派别会试图把外星人拉拢来征服其余人。
All right? All right.
好的？好的。
So having gone through these three theories,
于是我把这三种理论都梳理完后，
what I'm going to do is combine them together to create a comprehensive,
接下来我要把它们合并起来，形成一个完整的，
holistic, broad theory.
整体的、宽广的理论。
Of why societies rise and fall.
关于社会兴衰的原因。
Okay? All right.
好的？好吧。
And the problem with theories is they are simplistic
理论的难点在于它们过于简化。
and inaccurate and imprecise.
并且不准确且不精确。
So I'm, so I warn you that this theory has limitations.
于是我，先说这理论有局限。
But for our purposes,
但对我们而言，
what we want to do is have a working framework.
我们要做的事是有一个可用的框架。
And then when we apply this framework to concrete examples, we can better rethink it.
然后把这个框架套到具体例子上，我们就能更好地重新思考它。
refine this framework, okay?
再把框架细化一下，行吗？
Alright, so I warn you that this framework, there are a lot of problems with it,
好的，我先说这个框架有不少问题，
but it is a useful tool for us to analyze society in the past,
但它是我们分析过去社会的有用工具，
okay? Alright, so
好的，先说吧。
I'm going to make generalizations about how society is structured.
我将对社会结构作出概括。
So, at the core of society,
于是，社会的核心是……
the very powerful people,
最有权势的人们
these are certain families, okay?
这些是某些家族，明白吗？
These are the founding families of this nation.
这些是这个民族的创始家族。
And there's not that many of them, maybe 10, maybe 100, but at most 100.
并且并不多，或许十家，或许百家，最多百家。
So, if you go back to the Roman Empire, and the Roman Empire
于是，如果你回到罗马帝国，罗马帝国……
controlled most of Europe, as well as Anatolia,
它统治了欧洲大部分地区，也包括安那托利亚、埃及，面积很大，但实际上只有大约200个家族。
Egypt, it was a huge area, but really, there were only about 200 families
that controlled the Roman Empire, okay?
那统治罗马帝国，明白吗？
Alright, so, how these families express power,
好吧，那么，这些家族如何展现权力，
how they control power in society is through
他们如何通过社会掌控权力是通过
three mechanisms. Three pillars of power.
三种机制。权力的三大支柱。
And these three pillars are finance.
这三大支柱是财政。
Finance, we talked about last class, it's just central banking.
财政，我们上节课说过，它就是中央银行。
Alright? Second pillar is religion.
好吧？第二支柱是宗教。
Religion is just what people believe, how to control what people believe.
宗教就是人们的信仰，如何掌控人们的信仰。
Now, the religion of today is science and technology.
现在，今天的宗教就是科学与技术。
Science and technology. And the third pillar is
科学与技术。第三个支柱是智力。或者说间谍。
intelligence. Or spies.
好吧？现在，为了方便，...
Alright? Now, for the purpose of,
to save time, I'm not going to go too deeply into intelligence
为了省时，我不打算深入探讨智力与宗教，但以后课会讲，行吗？
and religion, but I will in future classes, okay?
我只要你记住，力量有三根支柱。
I just need you to remember that there are three pillars of power
I just need you to remember thatthere are three pillars of power
at the core of society. Finance, intelligence, and religion.
在社会核心。财政、情报与宗教。
And it's their nexus,
而它们的纽带，
their combination that
它们的组合
allows the elite to control everyone else.
让精英掌控其余众。
Okay? So, from this nexus,
好吧？于是从这纽带，
they will control all aspects of society,
他们将统御社会各个层面。
including schools,
包括学校，
including the military, including government,
包括军队，政府，
including the media, including culture,
包括媒体，文化，
including crime, the mafia.
包括犯罪、黑手党。
Okay? Every aspect of society that
好的？社会的每个方面，你能想象的，都在这股力量的掌控之中。
you can imagine is being controlled in some respect by this nexus of power.
Okay? Also you have like
好的？还有你会有像…
corporations, right? And
公司，对吧？
then, at the outer edge, are the people.
然后，在外缘是人们。
Okay? The people because
好吧？人们因为
they're so massive, the massive people, they're the ones who generate wealth for society.
他们很大，巨大的人民，他们是为社会创造财富的人。
So this system is designed to
于是这个系统就是这么设计的。
create as much energy as possible for the people.
为人民创造尽可能多的能量。
Okay? Energy. Because
好吧？能量。因为
the harder the people work, the more wealth is generated in society.
人们工作越努力，社会产生的财富越多。
Alright? So, a metaphor that we can use is this.
好了？我们可以用的一个比喻是这个。
Think of society as a corporation.
把社会想象成一家企业。
The people are the workers, right?
人们就是工人，对吧？
They're the ones who do the real work.
他们是实际工作的那一群人。
The elite, these families, are the owners.
精英，这些家族，就是所有者。
And these people in between, the middle class, are the managers.
而这中间的那一群人，即中产阶层，就是管理者。
Okay? So again, this is a very simple
好的？再说一次，这是一种很简单的比喻，
metaphor, and
而且它并不完全准确，但对分析很有用。
it's not accurate, but it's useful for analysis.
Okay? So, the families are the owners of the corporation,
好的？所以，家族是公司的所有者，
the people are the workers, the people in between, the managers are the managers.
人们是工人，夹在中间的则是管理者。
And we call these people the middle class.
我们把这些人称为中产阶层。
There have been other names for it in China before in history.
在中国历史上曾有其他称呼。
We call them the scholar officials, right?
我们称他们为文官，对吧？
Um, another name for them is something called the professional managerial class,
嗯，另一个称呼是专业管理阶层。
PMC. Also, another name for them is the
PMC。另一个称呼是小资产阶层。
petty bourgeoisie. Okay?
好？
Again, you don't need to know these names.
再说一次，你不必记住这些名称。
For the purpose of simplicity, we will just call them the middle class.
为简化起见，我们把它们称作中产阶层。
Alright. Does that make sense?
好的。这样说对吗？
Okay. So, having gone through the structure of society,
好了。既然已梳理完社会结构，
let's talk about what happens when society rises and falls.
我们来聊聊社会兴衰时的变化。
Okay? When it rises, the dynamic of these three groups, it's very interesting.
好的？当它兴起时，这三组的动态非常有趣。
When it rises, the families who
当它兴起时，家庭…
own the nation are happy
拥有民族的人民很高兴
to let the manager
让经理来掌控社会
control society. And this is what we call democracy, right?
这就是我们所说的民主，对吧？
And the managers are always providing feedback to the families
并且经理们总是向家庭反馈，并说我们应该更好地对待工人。
and saying, we should treat workers better.
如果我们更好地对待工人，那么…
If we treat workers better, then
they will work harder.
他们会更努力工作。
Okay? And at this point, things are great.
好的？此时一切都很顺利。
The people feel that they have a voice in the system,
人们觉得自己在体制中有发声的权利。
they're making good money, everyone's really happy.
他们赚了不少钱，大家都很开心。
But, what happens because of the
但是，因为什么而发生了什么。
elite overproduction is, these families produce
精英过度生产导致这些家庭产生。
too many children who want pieces of power.
孩子太多，想分得一点权力。
Basically, they want to spend money from the corporation.
基本上，他们想把公司钱花出去。
And now the corporation is in trouble.
现在公司陷入困境。
It's in debt. Okay?
它在债务中。好吗？
So at this point, what happens is this.
于是此时，发生的事是这样。
You would think the managers would say to the families, listen guys,
你会想，经理们会对家族说，听着，伙计们，
we need
我们需要
to be more fair to the people.
更公平对待人民。
But what really happens in reality is, the managers
但实际上发生的事是，经理们
exploit the people.
利用人民。
Okay? The managers will now deceive.
好的？经理们现在会欺骗。
They will lie to the people, they will commit fraud, they will exploit the people.
他们会对人民说谎，做欺诈，利用人民。
Why? The reason why is this.
为什么？原因就是这样。
What the managers really do is something called, um,
经理们真正做的事叫做，呃，……
rant seeking
发狂寻求
behavior. Okay?
行为。好的吗？
Ranting seeking behavior just means they have a certain power
发狂寻求行为只是指他们拥有某种力量
that they want to exploit in order to extract
他们想利用这种力量来提取
wealth from other people.
来自他人的财富。
So for example, the most classic example is, you own an apartment in Beijing, right?
比如说，最经典的例子是，你在北京拥有一套公寓，对吧？
So you rent it out to someone who needs to live in Beijing, and you collect rent.
你把它租给需要住在北京的人，然后收租金。
Well, this is true for, um, a lot of people.
好吧，这点对很多人都成立。
So, if you are a lawyer,
所以，如果你是律师，
you collect rent because
你收租金因为
only you can work in the court system.
只有你能在法院系统工作。
So if you want to sue someone, or if you want, if you have a contract dispute, you have to go to a lawyer, okay?
所以如果你想起诉某人，或者你有合同争议，你得去找律师，行吗？
The lawyer is collecting rent. And that's what the middle class,
律师在收租金。那就是中产阶层的事。
the professional managerial class do.
专业管理阶层所做的事。
They are rent seekers.
他们是租金寻求者。
Okay? And the way we're saying this is, guys,
好了？我们这么说吧，伙计们。
if you go to a company,
如果你去公司，你知道工人干啥，对吧？
you know what the workers do, right?
你知道经理干啥吗？
You know what the managers do?
They really don't do that much. Okay?
他们真的没干那么多。好吗？
And this is true for the middle class.
这对中产阶层也一样。
Like, um,
呃，像是……
the managers, the middle class, live very nice lives.
经理们、中产阶层过着非常舒适的生活。
And so, when the company's in trouble,
于是，当公司陷入困境时，
managers are like, well, I have a very nice life, I have a very nice job, but I don't really do anything,
经理们会说：好吧，我过得很不错，工作也很轻松，但我并没有真正干活。
so I'll probably be the first to get fired.
于是我大概会是第一个被解雇的人。
So they have to show their worth.
于是他们得证明自己的价值。
They have to prove their worth, and therefore, they exploit the workers.
他们得证明自己的价值，于是才会去剥削工人。
Okay? Do you understand? They push the workers harder to generate more wealth.
好的？你明白了吗？他们更用工人来创造更多财富。
Right? So, in the decline phase,
对吧？所以，在衰退阶段，
this is not really a problem.
这其实不算问题。
But what happens over time is,
但随着时间推移，
the conflict within
精英内部的冲突愈演愈烈。
the elite gets worse and worse.
Elite overproduction.
精英过剩产量。
And what will eventually happen is, they will form into factions
随后会形成各派，互相争夺权力。
that compete against each other for power.
各派相互竞争，争夺权力。
Okay? And when
好的？然后
that happens, then society becomes aligned into
那时，社会就会分化成各派。
factions. The factions will bring in certain elements of the middle class,
各派会把中产阶层的某些成员纳入其中。
which will then bring in certain elements of the people.
随后会把部分人群纳入其中。
And now,
现在，
what happens is civil war or revolution.
随后发生的是内战或革命。
And this marks the collapse of society.
这标志着社会的崩溃。
What's really important for us to remember is,
我们要记住的关键是，
this is a natural cycle, and no amount of external threat
这是一条自然循环，外部威胁无论多少都如此。
will change that
它会改变那种格局。
dynamic. Why? Because
为什么？因为
it's very common for these factions to align with
这些派系很常与……
mercenaries. Okay?
雇佣兵。好吗？
So, there's foreign invasions, not because
于是，出现外部入侵，并非因为……
some guy overseas is like, oh, this society is unstable, I'll come and invade.
某个海外人说：‘这社会不稳，我来入侵。’
What happens often is, a certain faction invites mercenaries
某个派系常常邀请雇佣兵
into the nation
进入该民族国家
as part of the power struggle.
作为权力争斗的一部分
And then the mercenaries realize, you know what, we can stick this for ourselves.
于是雇佣兵们意识到，咱们可以把这件事留给自己。
Alright? So, when
好了？那时，……
you reach the collapse phase, the society is much too insular,
当你们进入崩溃阶段，社会就已经太内向了。
much too wrapped with infighting to care about external threats.
已然已被内战缠绕，才会关心外部威胁。
And that's why if there's an alien invasion, it really wouldn't change anything.
正因如此，若有外来入侵，实则不改其形。
Okay? Alright?
好了？
Is this clear to you guys? So again, this is the model we're working with
这对你们来说清楚吗？所以再次说明，这是我们用来解释社会兴衰的模型。
to explain the rise and fall of societies.
首先，在这个体系里，…
At first, in this system,
the elite families are willing to let the major class
精英家族愿意让主要阶级…
incentivize and motivate the workers to do their best.
激励并激发工人发挥最佳表现。
And you do that through democracy, through openness,
并且你通过民主、通过开放来实现。
through meritocracy, through innovation.
通过才干制、通过创新。
But over time, as these elite families have more
但随着时间推移，随着这些精英家族拥有更多
and more children, and these children are engaged in ransom behavior,
以及更多孩子，这些孩子从事赎金行为，
they basically want to steal profits from the corporation,
他们基本想从公司偷取利润。
the corporation runs into trouble, and then
公司出现麻烦，随后管理层被迫用力压人，导致更大冲突。
managers are forced to coerce the people, which leads to greater conflict.
管理层被迫用力压人，导致更大冲突。
And eventually, over time, the collapse happens when
最终，随着时间推移，崩溃发生在…
society breaks up into different factions, which leads to civil war, or revolution,
社会分裂成不同派系，导致内战或革命。
or war. Okay.
或者战争。好的。
So that's the model we're working with.
所以这就是我们正在使用的模型。
Alright, any questions? Are you guys clear about this?
好的，大家有问题吗？你们对这点明白吗？
Yeah? What if they just like,
嗯？他们只是……
don't have that much children?
没那么多孩子吗？
Excuse me, what's the question?
请问，问题是什么？
Like, what if the family, the elite families don't have that much children?
比如说，家族，精英家族没那么多孩子吗？
Will this model still work?
这个模型还可行吗？
Oh, that's a great question. Okay.
哦，这是个好问题。好的。
So, what if families don't have that many children?
那么，如果家族没有那么多孩子呢？
Okay, that's a really interesting question.
好的，真是个有趣的问题。
And the answer is, these families first and foremost, want to have as many children as possible.
答案是，这些家族首先想尽可能多地生孩子。
Right? Because how do you pass on your power?
对吧？因为怎样才能把权力传给下一代？
... So,
...所以，
maybe the middle class don't want to have that many
也许中产阶层不想生那么多孩子，
children, but the elite will have a lot of children.
而精英阶层则会生很多孩子。
Because they need to be able to pass on their power and
因为他们需要能够把权力传给下一代并且……
privilege to their children.
……并把特权传给他们的孩子们。
In fact, the elite is first and foremost concerned
事实上，精英阶层首先关心……
with passing on their privilege to the next generation.
传给下一代的特权。
Okay? And that's why these elite families expand so fast.
于是，这些精英家族扩张得如此迅速。
And also, who wants to marry into elite families?
谁想嫁进精英家族呢？
Who wants to marry into them? Everyone.
谁想嫁进他们？人人都想。
Alright? And they have to
好吧？他们还得
marry into other families in order to maintain their power.
嫁进其他家族以维持权力。
Okay? So,
好吧？于是，
having children in a marriage is a way for the elite to maintain their power.
在婚姻中生子是精英维持权力的一种方式。
Okay? But that's a good question.
好吧？但这是个好问题。
Any more questions before I continue?
还有问题吗？
Okay. So, let us summarize what we've learned
好的。现在让我们总结到目前为止的内容并讨论。
so far and discuss
what is it
它是什么
that allows societies to rise
它是什么让社会得以兴起
and fall. So, we'll look at three phases.
以及衰落
The rise, the decline,
兴起、衰落、
and the collapse.
以及崩溃。
Okay? So, when I mean decline, I don't mean
好的？所以，我说衰落时，我指的是
like things are getting worse. I mean things aren't improving.
像事情变得更糟。我是说事情没有进步。
Okay? So, rise is when things get better.
好？所以，兴起是事情变得更好。
Decline is when things are stagnant or getting slightly worse.
衰落是事情停滞或略微变糟。
Collapse is when society is about to fall apart.
崩溃是指社会即将崩溃。
Okay? So,
好？所以，
if you look at these three particular phases of society, there are different characteristics.
若你观察社会的这三个特定阶段，便可见其各异特征。
When society rises, it is first and foremost open.
当社会兴起时，首先是开放的。
Open just means that you have opportunities
开放就是指你在社会中拥有社会流动的机会。
for social mobility in a society.
这些机会让你在社会中实现流动。
If you're a poor person, you can make money.
如果你是个穷人，你也能赚钱。
You can become wealthy.
你可以变得富有。
Your talent is appreciated.
你的才华会被认可。
It's a meritocracy. It's innovative.
它是才干制，创新型。
If you criticize society,
若你批评社会，
people are like, thank you for criticizing us because criticism makes us better people.
人们会说，感谢你批评我们，因为批评让我们更好。
Okay? There's open debate. Now, what's really interesting is
好的？有开放的辩论。现在，真正有趣的是
most young societies are open societies.
大多数年轻的社会都是开放的社会。
Okay? So, for example, in 1950s,
好的？比如说，在1950年代，
America was a democracy, right?
美国是民主国家，对吧？
China was communist.
中国是共产主义国家。
But, this is really interesting.
这才是重点。
In 1950s, they were both open societies.
1950年代，它们都是开放的社会。
You could criticize leaders. In fact, you were encouraged to criticize leaders.
你可以批评领导人。实际上，你被鼓励去批评领导人。
China was as democratic back then
当时的中国也是民主的。
as the United States. Okay?
就像美国一样。好吗？
So, it's not about political systems.
所以，关键不在于政治制度。
It's just about the what state you are in social development.
只是关于你所在的社会发展阶段。
So, if you're young, you're going to be open.
所以，如果你年轻，你就会变得开放。
You're going to be democratic. You're going to be meritocratic.
你会变得民主。你会变得才干主导。
You want to learn, so you will listen to criticism.
你想学习，所以你会听取批评。
Okay? That's the first great
好的？那是一个正在崛起的社会的第一个大特点。
characteristic of a society on the rise.
它是开放性。但，
It's openness. But,
when you reach a decline phase, guess what?
当你进入衰落阶段时，猜猜会怎样？
Society becomes bureaucratic.
社会变成官僚化。
Okay? Bureaucratic.
好吧？官僚化。
Why? Because, if we go back to this model,
为什么？因为，如果我们回到这个模型，[754]
as a company loses more and more money,
就像公司不断亏损，[755]
the managerial class is concerned with maintaining their jobs.
管理阶层只顾着保住自己的工作。[756]
So, they become bureaucrats.
于是他们变成官僚。
Okay? They have to prove their worth.
好吧？他们得证明自己的价值。
So, they create a lot of paperwork.
于是他们产生了大量文件。
They make everyone follow the rules.
他们让大家遵守规则。
Society becomes more and more bureaucratic.
社会变得越来越官僚化。
Then, in the collapse phase, society becomes
随后，在崩溃阶段，社会变得…
authoritarian. Okay?
专制。好吧？
Before, decline is about following the rules.
之前，衰落是遵守规则。
Now, it's just rule by force.
现在，只是用力来统治。
But, there's another way of saying this.
但，还有另一种说法。
In the rise phase, what matters is the consent.
在崛起阶段，关键是得到同意。
Okay? So, these three groups, the elite,
好吧？所以，这三组，精英，
the middle class, and the people, they're all working together
中产阶层与百姓，齐心协力，共促社会进步。已获同意。
to improve society. There's consent.
但，当你进入衰落阶段，...
But, when you hit the decline phase,
now, it's the deception. And
现在是欺骗。然后，
then, when you hit the collapse phase, it's coercion.
当你进入崛落阶段时是强迫。
So, let me give you an example. Let's just say
好了，我给你举个例子。
we are in the rise phase.
我们正处于崛起阶段。
Right? Well, we want to go to lunch.
对吧？我们想去吃午饭。
So, we discuss where we go to lunch.
于是我们讨论去哪里吃午饭。
I want to go to McDonald's, but you guys want to go to Pizza Hut or KFC.
我想去麦当劳，但你们想去必胜客或肯德基。
We have debate, and then, eventually,
我们辩论过，随后最终投票，谁想去谁赢。
we vote, and whoever wants to go, the majority wins.
投票后，人数多的决定去的地方。
Okay? That's the consent phase.
好的？那是同意阶段。
When we hit the decline phase, deception,
当我们进入衰落阶段，欺骗，
I'm the teacher. So, I say to you,
我是老师。所以，我对你说，
let's go to McDonald's because
我们去麦当劳吧，因为
Wong Fei will be there, or Jack Ma will be there, or
王飞会在那里，或者马云会在那里，或者
it's free hamburgers today.
今天有免费汉堡。
Okay? I'm lying to you to get what I want.
好的？我在撒谎是为了得到我想要的。
And then, in the collapse phase is, I say to you,
然后，在衰落阶段，我对你说，
I'm the teacher, and I will beat you up if you don't listen to me.
我是老师，如果你不听我的，我会揍你。
So, in the rise phase,
于是，在崛起阶段，
what matters, first and foremost, is unity of the people.
首先最重要的是人民的团结。
We're all working together. There's empathy.
我们齐心协力，彼此相感。
There's concern for other people.
有对他人的关心。
I want to be your friend.
我想成为你的朋友。
We need to work together to make society better.
我们需要一起努力，让社会更好。
Okay? But in the decline phase, it's really about stability.
好的？但在衰落阶段，真正是关于稳定。
It's about making sure
是关于确保
that society maintains a status quo.
社会保持现状。
Okay? When we reach the collapse phase, it is survival.
好的？当我们进入崩溃阶段时，就是生存。
Screw you. I want to live,
去你个……我想活着。
and if I have to kill you, I'll kill you. Alright?
如果我得杀了你，我就杀了你。好吧？
So, this is a map that
于是，这是一张地图
shows us what happens when society rises,
显示了社会崛起、衰落与崛溃时的变化。
declines, and collapses.
Now, what's really interesting about this is
现在，真正有趣的地方是
the timing, okay?
时机，好的？
So, if you actually look at
于是，如果你真正看一下社会的时间线，它的走势是这样的，好的？
society's timeline, it goes like this, okay?
society's timeline, itgoes like this, okay?
It's a steep rise,
它是陡峨的上升，下降缓慢，崛溃突发。
the decline is slow, and the collapse is sudden.
the decline is slow, andthe collapse is sudden.
So, people think, oh, decline,
于是，人们想，哦，衰落，你知道，事物变得更糟，但我们跟着这个趋势，我们还会在这里，实际上，
you know, things get worse, worse, but, you know,
你知道，我们跟着这个趋势，我们还会在这里，实际上，
we follow this trend, we'll still be here, but actually,
我们跟着这个趋势，我们还会在这里，实际上，
the collapse happens really fast.
崩溃发生得很快。
Why? The reason why is,
为什么？原因是，
this system cannot survive external shocks.
这个体系无法承受外部冲击。
So, external shocks is a perfect storm
于是，外部冲击就是一场完美的危机风暴。
of crises. So,
于是，另外一种说法是，可能是社会准备的方式。
another way of saying this is maybe society prepares for,
okay, if there's a plague, we'll do this.
好的，若出现瘟疫，我们就这么做。
If there's a climate crisis, we'll do this.
若出现气候危机，我们就这么做。
If there's a drought, we'll do this.
若出现旱灾，我们就这么做。
If there's a war, we'll do this. Okay?
若出现战争，我们就这么做。好吗？
What society is not prepared for is these things happening all at once.
社会未准备好的就是这些事一次性发生。
The plague, the drought,
瘟疫、旱灾，
war. So, remember, the revolution, they all happen at once.
战争。记住，革命，全部一次发生。
It's a perfect storm. And that's what leads to the collapse,
这是一场完美的风暴。正是它导致了崩溃。
because society is not prepared for this.
因为社会未准备好。
Okay? And why is society not prepared for this?
好吗？那为什么社会没有准备好呢？
Because when you hit the authoritarian phase,
因为当你进入专制阶段，你就不再能批评制度。
you're not allowed to criticize the system anymore.
The problem are those who speak out.
问题在于那些敢发声的人。
The problem is those who point out the problems of society.
问题在于那些指出社会问题的人。
In the rise phase, those who criticize society are the hearing, the hearers.
在崛起阶段，批评社会的人是听者，听者们。
They are appreciated.
他们受到赞赏。
They are rewarded. In the collapse phase, those who speak
他们得到奖励。在崩溃阶段，发声的人是社会的敌人。
out are the enemies of society.
And therefore, society cannot be prepared for any external threats,
于是，社会无法为外部威胁做准备，于是导致其崩溃。
which leads to its collapse.
于是，社会无法为外部威胁做准备，随后导致其崩溃。
Any questions? Okay.
还有问题吗？好的。
So, this is the ethical model that we're working with.
所以，这就是我们正在使用的伦理模型。
And again, we're going to apply it to the present,
再一次，我们将把它应用到现在，然后再应用到过去。
and then we're going to apply it to the past.
Okay? So, with this ethical model,
好的？所以，凭借这个伦理模型，
what we can do is make certain predictions
我们可以做的就是做出一些预测
about the future. So, I will make these predictions.
关于未来。于是，我会给出这些预测。
And I expect these things to happen in the next
我预计这些事将在接下来
five to ten years.
五到十年。
Five to ten years. Or ten to twenty years.
五到十年。或十到二十年。
Okay, I'm not I don't know the time frame.
好的，我不知道时间范围。
Okay? But I expect these things to happen.
好的？但我预计这些事会发生。
The first thing that's going to happen in the Western world is
第一件事在西方世界将会发生的就是
decline of democracy and freedom.
民主与自由的衰落。
So, remember, in the rise phase,
所以，记住，在兴起阶段，
society is democratic and open and meritocratic.
社会是民主、开放且以才干为本。
But as you move on, it becomes more bureaucratic and ultimately authoritarian.
但随着推进，变得更官僚化，最终成为专制。
Okay? So, we will see the United States,
好？所以我们将看到美国，
Europe, become much more authoritarian.
欧洲，变得更专制。
You will see the collapse of democracy and freedom in these nations.
你将看到这些国家的民主与自由崩溃。
And already we're seeing this happen in the United States,
而且我们已在美国看到这种情况出现，
where Trump is using more and more military to resolve issues.
在那里，特朗普越来越多地使用军力来解决问题。
Right? So, that's the first prediction.
对吧？所以，这就是第一个预测。
And this is going to happen throughout the Western world.
而且这将在西方世界各地发生。
Second thing is economic collapse.
第二件事是经济崩溃。
So, as people have less
于是人们的发声权越来越少，
and less right to speak up,
他们的发声权越来越少，
they feel less invested in the system, they're less willing to work.
Therefore, you have economic collapse.
因此，你们就会出现经济崩溃。
People don't believe in the system anymore.
人们不再相信这个体系。
Okay? The system is in crisis.
好了？体系正陷入危机。
This will lead to immigration.
这将导致移民。
The government is like, you know what, if the people don't want to work, screw them.
政府会说，明白吧，如果人们不想工作，那就算了。
Let's bring in immigrants to do the work.
让我们引进移民来干活。
Okay? This is, let's replace our population.
好的？这就是，咱们来换人。
But, the people are not going to sit back and take it, right?
不过，人们不会坐着等着接受的，对吧？
This leads to civil war.
这就导致内战。
People are not going to meet each other on the streets.
人们不会在街上相遇。
And the government is like, you know what,
政府会说，明白吧，
if we continue to let them fight, eventually
如果我们继续让他们打仗，最终
they're going to come after us. So, what we'll do is send them off to these stupid
他们会来追我们。于是我们安排他们去这些傻瓜的海外战争。好吗？
pointless wars overseas. Okay?
于是你现在有了傻瓜的战争。
So, now you have stupid wars.
So, now you havestupid wars.
Stupid foreign wars. And
傻瓜的海外战争。还有
these are my five predictions for the world for the next five, ten, twenty years.
这些是我对未来五、十、二十年世界的五个预测。
Okay? Europe and America
好的？欧洲和美国
will see less freedom and democracy.
将会看到自由与民主的减少。
The people are going to collapse, increase immigration,
人们将会崩溃，移民增加，
civil conflict, and then ultimately stupid foreign wars.
内战，随后又是傻瓜的海外战争。
And I'm not saying this happens
我并不是说它们按顺序发生。
in a sequence.
我说的是你会看到这五个阶段全部出现。
I'm saying you'll see all five phases.
我并不是说它们按顺序发生。
Okay? But they may happen in different order.
好的？但它们可能按不同顺序发生。
Any questions? Once it's clear to you guys.
还有问题吗？等你们明白后再说。
Yeah, thank you. Is there any chance that
好的，谢谢。还有机会吗？
the government tries to use a war to
政府试图用战争来做掩护？
distract the people? Like,
像是这样，
they're trying to hide all of the collapse of the society
他们正试图掩盖社会崩溃的全部过程。
and their country. Yeah.
和他们的国家。好的。
Yeah. That's a great question.
好的。很好的问题。
And the answer is, that's what wars are for.
答案是，战争正是为此而生。
It's to distract the people, right?
把它用来掩盖人们的注意力，对吧？
Because if you don't distract the people, they'll come and revolt against you.
如果不掩盖人们，他们就会来起义。
So, you either send them to a war or you could have a French Revolution on your hands.
所以，你要么把他们送去战争，要么让他们在你手里掀起法国大革命。
Right? That's your option. War or revolution?
对吗？那是你的选择。战争还是革命？
I think war is the better option.
我觉得战争是更好的选择。
That's why we're heading into a world at war.
这就是我们进入战争世界的原因。
Okay, no, no.
好的，没错，没错。
I'm saying like, if you don't send the people to war,
我说的是，如果你不把人们送去战争，
so you send them off to war to distract them.
于是你把他们送去战争来掩盖他们。
To get rid of them. Okay,
把他们去掉。好，
there's no right and wrong here, okay? Okay, alright.
这里没有对错，好的，好吧。
I apologize, okay? But one thing that you will learn in my class is, there's no right
我道歉，好的？但你会在我的课上学到的一件事是，没有对。
and wrong. There's no logic.
还有错。没有逻辑。
Okay? It's not like,
好？不是这样，
it is immoral to send people to war.
把人送去战争是非道德的。
I know that. Thank you very much. Okay, but I'm trying to explain to you how power works.
我知道。非常感谢。好了，我正试着向你解释权力的运作方式。
That's the theme of this class. I'm trying to explain to you how people in power think and behave.
这就是本课的主题。我正试着向你解释掌权者的思维与行为。
Alright? And, again, I keep on saying this.
好了？再说一次，我一直在说这件事。
I don't know if I'm right.
我不知道自己是否正确。
But what I'm doing is, I'm presenting a theory, a model that we can use
我现在做的是提出一个理论，一个我们可以用来做预测的模型。
to make predictions.
And if these predictions work out, if it actually happens, then our model,
如果这些预测落地，真的发生了，那么我们的模型就有一定准确性。
there's some accuracy to our model.
模型有一定准确性。
Okay? We'll have to refine our model, but there's some accuracy to it.
好的？我们会进一步完善模型，但它已经有一定准确性。
But hey, if tomorrow, Trump, Putin,
但如果明天，特朗普、普京、习一起说，咱们做最好的朋友，那我就错了。
Xi, all get together and say, let's be best friends,
then I'm wrong.
但如果明天，特朗普、普京、习一起说，咱们做最好的朋友，那我就错了。
Right? Okay?
对吧？好吗？
So that's what we're trying to do in this class.
所以这就是我们在这门课里要做的事。
We're not trying to argue what is right, what is wrong, what is just.
我们不是在争论什么是对的、错的、正义的。
Because, quite honestly, it doesn't matter.
因为，坦白说，没什么大不了的。
Morality doesn't matter here. It's about power.
道德在这里不重要，关键是权力。
We're trying to understand how the world works.
我们要弄懂世界是怎么运作的。
And if we do that, then maybe we can work together
如果我们这么做，或许我们能一起合作
and build a more just world.
并且建造一个更公正的世界
But first we need to figure out how the world really, really works.
但首先我们得弄清世界到底是怎样运作的
Okay? Any more questions?
好的？还有问题吗？
Okay. Great, guys.
好的。太好了，大家。
So we will continue this story
于是我们继续这个故事。
next class. I'll see you guys next class.
下节课见。下节课再见。